Let us hear
this Christian young man Hanskum.
Hanskung
he's written a book called infallible
question mark.
Author of being Christian
he says who is this man Hanskung I don't
know whether I'm pronouncing it
correctly.
Please forgive me. You know
the Scandinavian language is a bit
difficult on my tongue.
The 43-year-old Swissborn
Swissborn professor of dogmatic and
ecumenical theology and director of the
Institute of Ecumenical Studies at
Tubingan University in West Germany was
one of the select group of official
theologians appointed during the Vatican
2 council by Pope John himself.
known as the young proteé of modern
theology and consequently may not be
interpreted.
Uh he says now nowhere do
the books he says nowhere do the books
of the new testament claim to have
fallen directly from heaven.
Nowhere.
This is what our friend Hanskung says.
On the contrary, often enough, they
quite candidly emphasize quite candidly,
honestly, they emphasize
the human origin.
Luke chapter 1 verses 1 and two is
especially revealing on the origin of
the gospels.
Especially revealing.
What does it say? Luke 1:es 1 and 2.
Luke tells us, he doesn't talk about him
being tickled by the Holy Ghost or by
the Holy Spirit to write his words.
He
says here, verse two, just as those who
from the beginning were eyewitnesses and
ministers of the word delivered them to
us, it seemed good to me also.
If every Tom, Dick, and Harry people
less educated myself than myself, if
they can write volumes, me a physician,
one of the most learned of the followers
of Christianity at the time, why can't I
do a better job?
This is his inspiration. The others, you
can do it. You can do it. Why can't I?
I'm more learner than you. So he says,
"It seemed good to me also, having had
perfect understanding of all things from
the very first to write to you an
orderly account, most excellent
Theophilus."
The only thing he claims is
that the other writings are not orderly.
Mine will be an orderly account. Mark is
jumping here, there, and everywhere.
Mine won't be like that. Mine will be an
orderly book.
That is he does not claim
to be inspired by God or by the Holy
Ghost or by the Holy Spirit.
His
inspiration is the people that went
before him who had done the job.
And in this book of Luke
chapter 3 verse 23
we have the genealogy of Jesus.
It reads, "And Jesus
happened to be about
30 years of age when he began to preach
who being
in brackets in brackets as was supposed
the son of Joseph in brackets.
Now what's all this? Number one, if the
spirit of God is inspiring Luke to write
that,
this spirit of God didn't know how old
Jesus was.
Can you imagine this spirit of God
supposed to be God? The Christian
believes, the Pentecostals believe that
the father is God, the son is God, and
the Holy Ghost is God. But there are not
three gods but one God.
The Holy Ghost
is God, the spirit of God is God.
But
this God, if he inspired Luke, this God
didn't know how old Jesus was.
So he's saying about 30 years. God
doesn't know how old Jesus was when he
began is about 30 about.
He's not sure
when he began to preach. Now in the
latest translation, the word when he
began to preach is taken out.
You know
why? The question arises, God Almighty
waited for billions of years before
coming down to earth.
And from the age
from day one to the age of 30, he didn't
deliver one sentence for the benefit of
mankind.
What was he doing for 30 years?
What did he do? One sentence to help
mankind.
He did nothing.
Not one word, not one sentence.
So when he began to preach for 30 years,
he did nothing.
So they took the word
when he began to preaches out or the
modern translation of the King James
version the word is taken out and as was
supposed are in brackets
meaning Luke
Luke didn't write those words ask any
Christian scholar any Christian scholar
what the name these words in brackets
what do they mean what do they imply and
they will honestly confess that it means
that in the original manuscripts these
words were not there as was supposed was
not there.
These are the words of the
editors trying to help the reader. They
have a right.
They have a right. In the Quranic
translation, we find the same.
The
translator, he puts words in brackets,
meaning he's trying to convey to us that
look, the words are not there, but this
is what is implied.
He's trying to help
you. This help is appreciated
in the Bible also appreciated.
But now you see they can mint the word
of man is the word of man.
Now if Luke
was inspired then those words in
brackets are not inspired.
But what they have done now in the
Swedish Bible and the Danish Bible I
check them up.
The words are there
as was supposed are still there but the
brackets are thrown out.
You know now what it means
once the brackets are thrown out it
becomes the words of Luke and if Luke
was inspired they become the word of
God.
So the Christians are minting God's
word at their own leisure anytime they
want to.
They can put words in, put it
in brackets. Honest, very honest.
And
then take the brackets out in every
translation other than in English, in
the vernacular, in Zulu, Africans, in
Udu, in Swedish, in in Norwegian, in
every language of the world world other
than English.
The words are retained in
the brackets thrown out. Maybe the
Scandinavians don't know what brackets
mean.
And it's very true that we do not
believe in a verbal dictation.
We
believe in a complete total inspiration.
Subdu
Allahbar.