Allah, Exalted and Glorious is He, said:
"And they will approach one another, inquiring of each other."
Who are these people?
The people of Paradise.
May Allah make us among them.
O Allah, make us among them.
"And they will approach one another, inquiring of each other."
They will say, "Indeed, we were previously among our people fearful [of displeasing Allah]."
"So Allah conferred favor upon us"
"and protected us from the punishment of the Scorching Fire."
"Indeed, we used to supplicate Him before."
"Indeed, it is He who is the Beneficent, the Merciful."
Allah Almighty says:
"Whoever does righteousness - it is for his [own] soul;"
"and whoever does evil [does so] against it."
"And your Lord is not ever unjust to [His] servants."
Allah Almighty has also repeated this verse in Surah Al-Jathiyah:
"Whoever does a good deed - it is for himself;"
"and whoever does evil - it is against the soul."
"Then to your Lord you will be returned."
The one who did righteous deeds returns to Allah Almighty and enters Paradise.
And the one who did evil deeds returns to Allah Almighty and enters the Fire.
"Certainly did Allah confer [great] favor upon the believers"
"when He sent among them a Messenger from themselves,"
"reciting to them His verses"
"and purifying them"
"and teaching them the Book and wisdom,"
"although they had been before in manifest error."
"There has certainly come to you a Messenger from among yourselves."
"Grievous to him is what you suffer;"
"[he is] concerned over you and to the believers"
"is kind and merciful."
As for the criminal on the Day of Resurrection:
"The Day the Horn will be blown. And We will gather the criminals,"
"that Day, blue-eyed."
By Allah, I read its interpretation:
"Blue-eyed" means their faces will be blackened,
and their eyes blue from the intensity of fear and the terrors of the Day of Resurrection.
O my brothers, Allah Almighty says:
"The criminals will be known by their marks,"
"and they will be seized by the forelocks and the feet."
Their faces blackened,
their eyes blue,
shackled by their feet,
together with their hands.
We ask Allah for safety and well-being.
For this reason, Allah Almighty tells us:
"And fear a Day when no soul will suffice for another soul at all,"
"nor will intercession be accepted from it,"
"nor will compensation be taken from it,"
By Allah, no ransom will be taken from you, even if it were an earth full [of gold].
By Allah, no ransom will be taken from you, even if it were your father,
or your mother.
Allah Almighty says:
"They will be shown each other."
"The criminal will wish that he could be ransomed"
"from the punishment of that Day by his children,"
"And his wife"
Meaning his spouse,
"and his brother,"
"And his nearest kindred who shelter him,"
"And whoever is on earth entirely [so] then it could save him."
Because of this, Allah said:
"And fear a Day when no soul will suffice for another soul at all,"
"nor will intercession be accepted from it,"
"nor will compensation be taken from it, nor will they be aided."
"[It will be] on the Day the earth will be replaced by another earth, and the heavens [as well],"
"and all creatures will come out before Allah, the One, the Prevailing."
"The Day when We will fold the heaven like the folding of a [written] sheet for the records."
"As We began the first creation, We will repeat it."
"[That is] a promise binding upon Us."
"A promise binding upon Us. Indeed, We will do it."
"When the sky breaks apart,"
"And when the stars fall, scattering,"
"And when the seas are erupted,"
"And when the [contents of] graves are scattered,"
"A soul will [then] know what it has put forth and kept back."
"And when Paradise is brought near,"
"And when Hellfire is set ablaze,"
"A soul will [then] know what it has brought [with it]."
A soul will know what it has brought.
Therefore, on the Day of Resurrection,
Allah Almighty said about that great Day:
"No! When the earth has been leveled - pounded and crushed -"
"And your Lord has come and the angels, rank upon rank,"
"And Hell is brought [near] that Day."
It has seventy thousand reins,
and on every rein are seventy thousand angels dragging it,
so that it does not erupt upon the people of the gathering.
We ask Allah for safety and well-being.
"And Hell is brought [near] that Day."
"That Day, man will remember,"
"but how [i.e., what good] to him will be the remembrance?"
"He will say, 'Oh, I wish I had sent ahead [some good] for my life.'"
Oh, I wish I had prepared for that great Day.
So for that reason, we want to prepare ourselves from now.
"And Hell is brought [near] that Day."
What is the food of the people of Hell?
We ask Allah for safety and well-being.
"Indeed, the tree of Zaqqum"
"is food for the sinful."
"Like murky oil, it boils within bellies"
"like the boiling of scalding water."
"And you will see the people [as if] intoxicated"
"while they are not intoxicated; but the punishment of Allah is severe."
"Then He causes his death and provides a grave for him."
"Then, when He wills, He will resurrect him."
Listen to what Allah Almighty said about our creation:
"And certainly did We create man from an extract of clay."
This is my story and yours.
"Then We placed him as a sperm-drop in a firm lodging."
"Then We made the sperm-drop into a clinging clot,"
"and We made the clot into a lump [of flesh],"
"and We made [from] the lump, bones,"
"and We covered the bones with flesh;"
"then We developed him into another creation."
"So blessed is Allah, the best of creators."
This is in this world.
"Then indeed, after that you are to die."
"Then indeed you, on the Day of Resurrection, will be resurrected."
By Allah, my brothers, we will be resurrected.
Allah Almighty says:
"And the Horn will be blown,"
"and whoever is in the heavens and whoever is on the earth will fall dead"
"except whom Allah wills."
"Then it will be blown again,"
"and at once they will be standing, looking on."
The Horn will be blown,
"and suddenly they will be [alert] upon the earth's surface."
"and at once they will be standing, looking on."
The Horn will be blown,
"and suddenly they will be hastening from the graves to their Lord."
"They will say, 'O woe to us!"
"Who has raised us up from our sleeping place?'"
"[The reply will be], 'This is what the Most Merciful had promised,"
"and the messengers told the truth.'"
"It will not be but one blast,"
"and at once they are all brought present before Us."
Brought present before Allah.
"Their eyes humbled,"
"humiliation will cover them."
"That is the Day which they had been promised."
Allah Almighty says:
"And they ask you about the mountains,"
"so say, 'My Lord will blow them away with a blast.'"
"'And He will leave the earth a level plain;'"
"'you will not see therein a depression or an elevation.'"
On the Day of Resurrection,
"That Day, they will follow the caller [with] no deviation therefrom,"
"and [all] voices will be stilled before the Most Merciful,"
"so you will not hear except a whisper [of footsteps]."
"That Day, no intercession will benefit"
"except [that of] one to whom the Most Merciful has given permission"
"and has accepted his word."
"That Day, no intercession will benefit"
"except [that of] one to whom the Most Merciful has given permission"
"and has accepted his word."
"He knows what is [presently] before them and what will be after them,"
By Allah, I read the interpretation earlier:
"He knows what is before them"
On the Day of Resurrection,
Allah knows your destiny,
whether you are in Paradise.
And Allah knows your destiny whether you are in the Fire.
"He knows what is before them and what will be after them,"
"but they do not encompass it in knowledge."
"And [all] faces will be humbled before the Ever-Living, the Sustainer of existence."
"And he will have failed who carries injustice."
"But he who does of righteous deeds while he is a believer"
"he will neither fear injustice nor deprivation."
Allah will not wrong you, by Allah.
He will not decrease [your reward],
Allah Almighty will not wrong you,
nor will He add to your bad deeds,
nor will Allah Almighty deprive you of your right.
Rather, He increases your good deeds until you enter Paradise.
So my brothers,
The Day of Resurrection, if you knew of its terror,
You would flee from your family and homelands.
The Day the sky splits apart from its terror,
And the hair of the children turns white from it.
A frowning, severe Day, its evil
Spreading among creation, of great magnitude.
These people on the Day of Gathering will be divided into two groups:
"And the Day the Hour appears - that Day they will become separated."
"And as for those who had believed and done righteous deeds,"
"they will be in a garden [of Paradise], delighted."
"But as for those who disbelieved and denied Our verses"
"and the meeting of the Hereafter, those will be brought into the punishment."